Guide to the Robert E. Treuhaft Papers TAM.664
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Robert E. Treuhaft Papers
1893-2002
1960-1980
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Treuhaft, Benjamin
Mitford, Jessica, 1917-1996
Treuhaft, Robert E.
Romilly, Constancia
TAM.664
5.5 Linear Feet in 5 record cartons, one manuscript box and one oversized box.
Robert E. Treuhaft (1912-2001) a radical left-wing attorney prominent in progressive and New Left politics in the San Francisco Bay Area, was known for his work as a civil rights and civil liberties attorney as well as representing New Left organizations and individuals, such as the Free Speech Movement. He was perhaps equally well-known for his wife, muckraking writer Jessica Mitford, radical and rebellious daughter of a family of conservative British aristocrats and author of a best-selling expose of the funeral industry, The American Way of Death, for which Treuhaft contributed the research. Treuhaft and Mitford joined the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA) in 1943 and remained members until 1958. Treuhaft provided legal representation for "unfriendly" witnesses subpoenaed by the U.S. House of Representatives' Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC); he himself and Mitford were called to testify before the Committee in 1953, where they also failed to cooperate with the Committee by "naming names." As a consequence of this, and their other political activities Treuhaft and Mitford were constantly surveilled and frequently harassed by federal, state, and local government agencies. The collection consists of of legal case files, business and personal correspondence, internal memos, FOIA files, published and unpublished writings, newspaper clippings.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Benjamin Treuhaft and Constancia Romilly in 2015. The accession number associated with this donation is 2015.09.
Appraisal
Routine worker compensation case files were discarded, with the exception of a sample retained to illustrate this aspect of Robert Treuhaft's practice; duplicate documents were also discarded. Strictly personal documents have been returned to the donors.
Arrangement
Organized into eleven series.
I, Biographical
II, Correspondence - Business
III, Correspondence - Personal
IV, Law Office/Partnerships
V, Legal Case Files
VI, Miscellaneous
VII, Organizations
VIII, Political Issues/Activism
IX, Research
X, Writings
XI, Wills
Arrangement is mostly in alphabetical order by folder title and in chronological order when there is more than one folder with the same title. Correspondence combines incoming and outgoing letters.
Historical/Biographical Note
Robert Edward Treuhaft, a radical left-wing attorney prominent in progressive and New Left politics in the San Francisco Bay Area, was born in the Bronx, New York City, in 1912, the oldest child of Hungarian Jewish immigrants. He attended public schools and became the first person from his Brooklyn high school to be admitted to Harvard University. He graduated from Harvard in 1934, and obtained a law degree from Harvard Law School in 1937. After graduation from law school he worked for a labor law firm in New York City for, whose clients included the International Ladies Garment Workers Union. In 1941, he took a position in Washington, D.C., with the enforcement division of the wartime Office of Price Administration (OPA). At OPA, he met his future wife, Jessica Mitford Romilly (known as Decca Mitford, radical and rebellious daughter from a famously eccentric and conservative family of British aristocrats), who was also working at the agency. In 1943 Treuhaft left the OPA and moved to the West Coast to work for the War Labor Board's San Francisco office and to join Mitford, who had also taken a job in San Francisco. They married soon after their arrival to the Bay Area. In 1945, Treuhaft joined the law firm of Gladstein, Grossman, Sawyer & Edises. At Gladstein he represented West Coast labor unions expelled from the CIO as a result of accusations that they were Communist-led or dominated. A few years later he and Bertram Edises established their own firm. They became well-known as civil rights attorneys when they successfully defended, Jerry Newson, an 18-year-old African American man, against a framed-up murder charge. Treuhaft also acted as counsel for the East Bay Civil Rights Congress from 1949 to 1956, advocating for clients suffering racial discrimination and he brought pioneering police brutality suits against the Oakland Police department.
In 1963, Treuhaft and Doris "Dobby" Walker (a long-time friend and political ally of Treuhaft and Mitford's) founded their own law firm (through the years joined by different partners, beginning with Malcolm Burnstein, as well as numerous young associates and interns, including future Secretary of State Hillary Rodham Clinton during the summer of 1971). Throughout the 1960s and 1970s Treuhaft, Walker & Burnstein represented clients in civil rights cases (as well as handling more general law, such as wills and divorces, for clients among the African American and progressive communities in the area); they also became well-known for representing New Left organizations and activists. Treuhaft acted as counsel for the Free Speech Movement, representing the more than 700 students arrested at the University of California at Berkeley during a two-day sit-in in 1964. He himself was also arrested during the sit-in, at the direction of then- Assistant District Attorney of Alameda County, Edwin Meese, who later became Attorney General during the Reagan presidency. In addition, Treuhaft and his firm represented anti-Vietnam War protesters, Black Panther Party, the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC), the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE), and University of California students and town residents arrested during the struggle over People's Park in Berkeley. Treuhaft's expansive vision of civil liberties included child custody cases in which he defended clients whose parental rights being challenged on the basis of their cultural lifestyles. As part of his lifelong concern for the rights and welfare of ordinary citizens, Treuhaft became interested in consumer rights and protections. In 1962 he co-wrote a handbook for California lawyers on debtors' rights. When he became aware of deceptive practices by funeral homes he helped to found the Bay Area Funeral Society to serve as a model for simpler and less expensive funerals, and took a year's leave of absence from his law practice to research the topic more deeply. He also assisted his wife with writing The American Way of Death, an expose on the funeral industry based on his research. Published in 1963, the The American Way of Death became an enormous (and to the Treuhafts, entirely unexpected) success, a bestselling book, and made Mitford--already a published writer--famous as a muckraking journalist, known for her special blend of investigative journalism with political satire. As a consequence of the publicity surrounding the American Way of Death Treuhaft was appointed by California Governor Jerry Brown as a public member to the California State Board of Funeral Directors and Embalmers (much to the consternation of funeral directors throughout the country).
Treuhaft also participated in local and community politics. In 1966 he ran (and lost the race) for District Attorney for Alameda County against the longtime rightwing incumbent Frank Coakley. He served several terms on the board of the Consumers Cooperative of Berkeley (better known as the Berkeley Co-Op), a small group member-run supermarkets in the Bay Area, including one after a hotly-contested election campaign, in which he ran on a slate of progressives. He was also instrumental in getting the Co-Op board to pass a resolution cutting off its contributions to the national organization of co-operative stores, the Cooperative League of America, because it had accepted funds from the CIA.
In 1982, Treuhaft and Walker dissolved their partnership. From this time through his retirement in 1997 Treuhaft began to specialize in workers' compensation cases and appeals to the Social Security Administration. Robert Treuhaft was also active in progressive attorneys' organizations such as the National Lawyers Guild (he served as a vice president and was honored by it, along with Mitford, with a testimonial dinner in 1985). As a member of the International Association of Democratic Lawyers (IADL) he served on an mission to Portugal in 1964 to investigate torture of political prisoners (as a result he and fellow commission members were arrested and expelled from the country by the authoritarian government of Antonio Salazar), and to Okinawa in 1969 to investigate human rights violations by the United States.
Treuhaft and Jessica Mitford joined the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA) in 1943 and remained members until 1958. Treuhaft provided legal representation for "unfriendly" witnesses subpoenaed by the U.S. House of Representatives' Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC). He himself and Mitford were called to testify before the Committee in 1953. They refused to "name names," (that is, identify for the Committee their own or others' political affiliations or memberships). Treuhaft took issue publicly with those who did, including in a 1984 article in The Nation on his Harvard class' 50th reunion. As a consequence of this, and their other political activities the Treuhafts were constantly surveilled and frequently harassed by federal, state, and local government agencies, up to and including being denied passports.
Treuhaft and Mitford raised two children to adulthood—Benjamin, their second son (another son, Nicholas, died at age ten), and Constancia "Dinky" Romilly, Mitford's daughter from her first marriage. Jessica Mitford died in 1996. Treuhaft completed The American Way of Death Revisited (published 1998), the update of The American Way of Death Mitford had been working on at the time of her death. Robert Treuhaft died on November 11, 2001.
Related Archival Materials
Jessica Mitford Collection, Rare Books and Manuscripts Library, Ohio State University. Jessica Mitford Papers, Harry Ransom Center, University of Texas at Austin.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of legal case files, business and personal correspondence, internal memos, FOIA files, published and unpublished writings, newspaper clippings, and other materials that document much of the public and political life, and some of the private life, of Robert Treuhaft. They also document political/civil liberties legal cases stemming from a number of historic events of the 1960s, the Free Speech Movement, People's Park, and the march on the California State capitol by members of the Black Panther Party.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Separated Materials
1/4" audiotapes originally in folder "Siegel, Dan People v. folder (give #?)
Bibliography
Larsen, Robert. Treuhaft, Robert E. Berkeley Historical Society. Oakland, California, 1988-1989. "Left-Wing Political Activist and Progressive Leader in the Berkeley Co-op Robert E. Treuhaft." Consumers Cooperative of Berkeley Oral History Collection. http://content.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/kt4x0nb0bf/
Lewis, Paul. "Robert Treuhaft, 89, Lawyer Who Inspired Funeral Exposé." New York Times, December 2, 2001. http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/02/us/robert-treuhaft-89-lawyer-who-inspired-funeral-expose.html
Lisker, Susan. "Treuhaft, Walker, Brown and Cooper: An Unusual Law Firm." University of California, Berkeley, 1976.
Mitford, Jessica. A Fine Old Conflict. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1977.
"National Lawyers Guild Bay Area Testimonial Dinner 1985--Jessica Mitford, Robert Treuhaft Honorees." (program)
Oliver, Myrna. "Robert Treuhaft, 89; Crusading Attorney." Los Angeles Times, November 16, 2001. http://articles.latimes.com/2001/nov/16/local/me-4896
Wilmot, Ingrid. "Dining In,' [profile of Robert Treuhaft], San Francisco Magazine, May 1965, p.54.
Legal files.; Lawyers -- Political activity -- United States.; Wills; Correspondence.; Legal correspondence.; People's Park (Berkeley, Calif.) -- History.; Black-and-white photographs.; Audiotapes.; Black Panther Party; Treuhaft, Benjamin; Free Speech Movement (Berkeley, Calif.); International Association of Democratic Lawyers; Romilly, Constancia
- Biographical, 1893-2002
  Scope and Content Note
  Documents in this series include passports (which document Treuhaft's travels as early as the summer of 1937 when he visited England, France and Italy, as well as, Austria, Germany and Hungary, as well as later travels to England, Hungary, Portugal, and the Soviet Union), report cards and grades from elementary school as well as for Harvard University, class notes for an evidence class at Harvard Law School, announcements and notes for a 50th reunion of his Harvard class about which he wrote an article in The Nation; copies of his FBI and CIA "files" obtained through FOIA requests. Correspondence and receipts in the "red-baiting" folders (as they were originally labeled by Treuhaft or his office staff) document extensively his efforts to defend himself from attempts to dismiss him from his job at the Office of Price Adminstration on political grounds. These same files contain numerous newspaper clippings, leaflets and publications report on the course of much of his political activity, albeit often in a biased or distorted manner, including accusations and attacks in the right-wing press and a scurrilous newsletter from a local Communist Party group; even an insurance claim that documenting what may have be a politically motivated deliberate damage to Treuhaft's automobile.
  - Datebook, Calendar, and Address Books, 1933-1934, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Datebook, Calendar, and Address Book, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Datebook, Calendar, and Address Books, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Datebook, Calendar, and Address Books, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Elementary and Junior High School Report Cards; Diptheria Vaccination Certificate, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - FOIA - Documents from CIA, 1964-1969, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - FOIA - Documents from FBI, 1945-circa 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Freedom of Information Act - Suit Against the FBI and National Archives, 1975-1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Harvard University, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Harvard University - Class of 1934 - 50th Reunion, 1983-1984, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Judge Pro Tem, 1989-1994 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Memorial Commitee for Robert Treuhaft, Feb 23, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Mitford, Jessica - Newspaper Clippings, 1981, 1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1944-1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Notes For Evidence Class at Harvard Law School, circa 1934-1937 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Oral History - Robert Treuhaft - Correspondence and Publications Re, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Passports, 1937, 1958, 1969, 1974, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Red-Baiting, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Red-Baiting, 1948, 1953-1957 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Red-Baiting, 1964-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - San Francisco Magazine - May 1965 Issue (Box 6 (oversized), Folder 2)
  - Treuhaft (Extended) Family Records, 1893-1921 (Box 6 (oversized), Folder 2)
    Announcements of deaths, mainly individuals from the Zipser family, who were probably relatives of the Treuhaft's father or mother, published in Hungarian and German.
  - Treuhaft for (Alameda County, California) District Attorney Election Campaign - Correspondence, Press Releases, Leaflets, Clippings, Rubber Stamp, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Treuhaft for (Alameda County, California) District Attorney Election Campaign - Campaign Contributions Records, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 70th Birthday Celebration, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence - Business, 1957-2000, undated
  Documents in this series concern business outside of Treuhaft's law firm. Most are between Treufhaft and his correspondents, but there are also occasional letters to or from Jessica Mitford. Many of these concern literary matters, including Treuhaft's and Mitford's letters to and from Robert Gottlieb, their editor at Knopf, about The American Way of Death Revisited, editors of letters of Mitford's published letters, and with potential and actual biographers of Mitford. Because Treuhaft and Mitford often had, or developed close relationships with business correspondents (they were often friends or became friends) a considerable amount of the correspondence mixes both personal and business matters.
  - Correspondence, 1957-2001 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Carlson, Lisa, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chisholm, Anne (Re Jessica Mitford Letters), 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Gottlieb, Robert--Jessica Mitford, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Gottlieb, Robert--Robert Treuhaft, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Kroeger, Brooke, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Lovell, Mary (Re Jessica Mitford Biography), 1991-2000 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Jessica Mitford (Memorial) Professorship (proposed), 1996 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence - Personal, 1931-2001
  Correspondents include extended family – Treuhaft's sister and cousins, and Mitford's family, including one of her sisters, Deborah Cavendish, Dutchess of Devonshire. Friends include writers Kay Boyle and Gail Sheehy, with short notes from correspondents as diverse as former cliients, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Shana Alexander, and Hillary Clinton (as a law student she served a summer internship at Treuhaft's firm; her communication is a note extending condolences to Treuhaft from herself and then-President Clinton upon Mitford's death).
  - Correspondence, 1931-1996 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1997-1999 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Alexander, Shana (elephants), 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Family: Benjamin and Robert Treuhaft - Cuba Trip, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Family: Cavendish, Deborah (Dutchess of Devonshire), 1997-2000 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Family: Guiness, Desmond and Penelope, 1997-2001 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Family: Romilly, Constancia "Dinky", 1997-2000 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Family: Treuhaft Family, 1961-1994 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Lane, Laura, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Robert Treuhaft Health, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Travel - England, Europe, Cuba, 1994, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Law Office/Partnerships, 1944-1993
  While a few formal partnership documents are included, the bulk of the materials in this series are memos and correspondence by office staff as well as attorneys, that pertain to the business and finances and management of running a law firm. Unusually lively and personal for these types of documents, they also offer a window into the tensions as well as the rewards of working for a firm whose cases pursued equity and democracy and translating those principles into a workplace that reflected them without compromising efficiency and good management. "1440 Broadway" refers to the street address of the office building in Oakland, California, where many of these law firms were located, as well as the offices of progressive organizations and other radical attorneys over more than three decades.
  - 1440 Broadway - Correspondence and Clippings, 1944-1981 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - 1440 Broadway - Correspondence and Clippings, 1982-1993 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - 1440 Broadway - Correspondence and Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Edises & Treuhaft; Edises, Treuhaft, Grosman and Grogan - Financial Reports, 1950-1962 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Edises, Treuhaft, Grossman & Grogan - Partnership Dissolution, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Legal Case Files
  Cases in this series are mostly related to civil rights and civil liberties and efforts to combat racial discrimination and police brutality; they include both those in which Treuhaft's partners or associates represented clients as well as those for which Treuhaft was the lead attorney. (If not otherwise noted, attorneys are indicated by their initials on their original folders: RET for Treuhaft, DOB for Doris Walker, MB for Malcolm Burnstein). Clients--defendants, plaintiffs, or targets of grand jury investigations--are mainly progressive or leftwing political organizations and individuals associated with these organizations or individuals involved in cases springing from political events. Organizations and individuals associated with them include the Black Panther Party, Bobby Seale and Huey Newton; the Free Speech Movement (from the beginning, with the more than 700 arrested, through the appeals process), Mario Savio and Treuhaft himself; Civil Action Day Committee (clients arrested in a civil disobedience action at a draft induction center to protest conscription); and Berkeley Barb (newspaper), Robert Scheer, John Poland. Briefs, statements and correspondence document Malcolm Burnstein's defense of eighteen members of the Black Panther Party arrested after its widely-publicized demonstration in front of and inside the California state capitol while armed with deliberately unconcealed rifles. Documents from this file include handwritten statements from each of the defendants. Files for Treuhaft clients arrested during the events of People's Park include what appear to be police surveillance photographs and audiotape obtained during the legal discovery process. Case files for two child custody cases involving controversy over parents' lifestyle include the widely-publicized Mark Painter case. Treuhaft also represented fellow Bay Area radical attorneys Faye Stender and Charles Garry (both in politically-associated contempt of court-related cases). A small sample of workers' compensation cases illustrate Treuhaft's work in this field, in which he specialized nearly exclusively during the last decade of his legal practice.
  - Avakian, Robert et al vs. Advan Inc., 1967 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Black Panthers (Demonstration in and around California State Capitol and related cases), May 2, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Berkeley Barb - John Poland, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Boyle, Kaye - "Santa Rita", 1973 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Civil Action Day Committee - People v., 1967-1972 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Comfort, Mark - People v., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Dayton, Mark B. (Subpoenaed by Grand Jury), 1972 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Douthit, Florence vs. City of Berkeley et al (re People's Park conflict), 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Ester, Semillion (newspaper clippings), circa 1980 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Free Speech Movement - Legal Documents and Correspondence, 1964-1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Free Speech Movement - Appeals, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Frisby, Mrs. Barbara (child custody), 1972-1973, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Garry, Charles - Petition for Writ, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Goldberg, Arthur - People v. (re People's Park conflict), 1969-1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - McKinney, Gene Alan [Newton, Huey P. - People v. in Matter of Gene Alan McKinney], 1968, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Mihans, et al v. Municipal Court - Writ of Review (tenant-landlord dispute), 1970 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Neville, Robert v. Finnish Sauna Baths (racial discrimination), 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 8)